A Guide to the Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #6903
Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen Collection 1867-1895
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
6903
26 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit 1962 Nov 14
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - "Idyls of Norway and Other Poems" [1882], 1893 Nov 4; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Sonnets on "Evolution"; begins "I am the child of earth & air & sea.. ."]
  - "Three Sonnets", n. d.; AMsS, 3 p.
    [Three sonnets beginning, "If I should lose thee, Darling.. ."; "I saw thee drifting.. ."; and "I wonder oft why God.. ."]
- Letters
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen to Harriet Jackson, 1877 Jan 21; ALS, 1 p.
    [Refuses to part with autograph letters of Ivan Tourguenett at Jackson's request; promises to ask Tourguenett to write a few lines for her which he will forward to her.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, Ithaca, New York, to Mrs. Foot, 1878 Jan 23; ALS, 4 p.
    [Acknowledges her 2 letters; says he is overburdened with literary and professional work and apologizes for not answering sooner; mentions his failure to meet her in New York City; expects to go to Europe for a year's stay; talks at length about evolution, a subject which haunts him; looks at evolution theory in its Goethe aspect; says he has written a series of "scientific sonnets!" soon to be published, to clear his mind of the subject of evolution; looks forward to a long literary talk with her; notes she is working on a story or a book.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York to [ Alexander Wilson] Drake, [ New York], 1883 May 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses Norwegian painter Hammerstead who plans to settle in [ New York]; asks for Drake's help in bringing Hammerstead's paintings before the public.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, Nantucket, Massachusetts, to [Richard Watson] Gilder, [ New York], 1886 Aug 3; ALS, 1 p.
    [Encloses short poem which he feels good about; discusses a story he is working on.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to John M. Bunt, 1889 Oct 2; ALS, 1 p.
    [Responds to Bunt's request for him to recall an important incident in his life by saying he has nothing to offer other than his birth, which was to long ago for him to remember it.]
  - Charles Scribner, New York, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1891 Oct 16; ALS, 2 p.
    [Agrees to publish a volume of juvenile stories,
    Boyhood in Norway
    , 1892, for Boyesen in the autumn of the following year; discusses term of publication.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, [ New York], 1891 Nov 3; ALS, 2 p.
    [Sends the requested ballad intended for recitation, "The [ ] of A Song"; hopes it will suit him but promises not to be offended if it does not.]
  - Charles Scribner, New York, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, 1891 Nov 11; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he will gladly publish Boyesen's
    Essays on German Literature
    , 1892; says there will be a market for the book; offers a 10 percent; royalty; mentions juvenile stories.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to [Samuel Sidney] McClure, [ New York], 1891 Dec 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Sends postage stamps for the return of the manuscript of his ballad; says he will have no further communication with McClure; marvels at his "cheek."]
  - Charles Scribner, New York, to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, 1892 Oct 18; TLS, 1 p.
    [Encloses a report on
    and a royalty cheque; says Scribner's is willing to publish a companion volume,
    Essays on Scandinavian Literature
    , 1895, provided that certain conditions are met.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Jan 14; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks for a November 1884 copy of
    The Dial
    , in which a story of his on Hans Christian Anderson appears; intends include the story in
    congratulates Browne on the appearance and literary excellence of
    . ]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Jan 26; ALS, 4 p.
    [States that he has written an article, not in the form of a book review, on Henrik Ibsen's play
    "Love's Comedy,"
    which has not yet been translated into English; offers his article to
    for $20, though he could get twice that amount, because he values
    mentions Hans Christian Anderson story, his busy lecture schedule.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Samuel Sidney McClure, [ New York], 1893 Feb 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Decides to interpret his novel to write article on William Dean Howells at once; requests prompt payment; asks to see proof before article goes to print; says he could easily sell the article to
    Cosmopolitan
    , should McClure not be pleased with it.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Mar 24; ALS, 3 p.
    [Sends for approval if article on Henrik Ibsen, "The Wild Duck," which will be included in
    Essays On Scandinavian Literature
    expects $20 for it.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Mar 29; ALS, 1 p.
    [Assures him that there is no particular hurry to publish "The Wild Duck" as Scribner's will not put out
    before 1895.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 May 7; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks him to watch out for an article of his literary criticism which will appear in
    The Forum
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Jul 28; ALS, 2 p.
    [Acknowledges $20; speaks highly of and recommends writers [James] Brander Matthews, George Edward Woodberry, and William Hamilton Gibson whom he likens to John Burroughs; says that George Parsons Lathrop is interesting only to the select since he became Catholic.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1893 Sep 20; ALS, 3 p.
    [Says Browne's letter reached him at Columbia via Geneva and Chicago; gives his impression of "The Fair," Columbia Exposition 1893 in Chicago; sums it up as the most magnificent the world has to offer; is especially taken with the wonder of electrical illumination.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, Southampton, Long Island, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1894 Jul 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Asks for the proof of "The Wild Duck" to be sent to Long Island, if Browne decides to publish it.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1894 Oct 6; ALS, 2 p.
    [Requests a copy of article on Hans Christian Anderson, published in
    November 1884; intends to include it in
    , to be published by Scribner 's; names other essays he will include in the volume.]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to Francis Fisher Browne, [ Chicago], 1894 Oct 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he has found his own copy of the story on Hans Christian Anderson. ]
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, New York, to J. Howard Rhoads, 1895 Jan 20; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he has not published the lectures Rhoads refers to and that he does not intend to do so for a few years; says the substance of the lectures, with the exception of the lecture on Algernon Charles Swinburne, is in
    Literary and Social Silhouettes
    1894.]
  - Elizabeth Keene Boyesen, Southampton, to William Stephen Rainsford, New York City, n. d. Friday; ALS, 12 p.
    [Discusses the quality of Sunday school for children at St. George's; gives reasons for sending her son to St. Barthlomus; pleads with him to persuade her husband to remain a member of St. George, the church they were both confirmed in; expresses thoughts on Robert Browning. ]
- Miscellaneous
  - Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, [ New York] to Scribner & Co., New York City, 1875 Nov 29; Receipt, 1 p.
    [Receipt for the sum of $105.50.]